<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>MetaHikari</title><link>http://metahikari.github.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://metahikari.github.com/feeds/About%20MetaHikari.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2013 08:37:14 +0900</lastBuildDate><item><title>About MetaHikari</title><link>http://metahikari.github.com/about-metahikari.html</link><description>&lt;h2&gt;Static, but Changing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to MetaHikari, an experiment in static site blog design!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MetaHikari is generated using &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;, a Python-based, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Static_web_page"&gt;static site&lt;/a&gt; generator.  I utilize &lt;a href="http://github.com/"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; for free hosting.  Since my site is unchanging until I update it, there is no need to worry about maintaining a database for dynamic content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More importantly, MetaHikari is where I write about my struggles and (minor) triumphs in the worlds of &lt;strong&gt;programming&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Brazilian jiu jitsu (BJJ)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please forgive the various design/content changes that will take place as I get things up and running!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learning to Code the Hard Way&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming is an activity that can be learned pretty much anywhere these days.  There is a long list of options for online learning, such as coursera and opencourseware.  I am perhaps a bit old-fashioned and am learning largely through textbooks and friends.  I write about my experiences learning code in Tokyo, Japan.  Hopefully, I will also attend and write about various programming related meetups in Tokyo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog will document my studies, so it may be of interest to other wannabe hackers and beginners.  Learning to code has so far been extremely intellectually rewarding, so I would like to share my enthusiasm about code and (eventually) make some cool stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Gentle Art&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A submission-based, grappling martial art, BJJ places an emphasis on ground fighting and full-speed sparring.  Something I love about BJJ is that it challenges both my body and mind.  Indeed, the &lt;em&gt;mental&lt;/em&gt; aspect is equally as satisfying as the physical training.  I train at an awesome &lt;a href="http://bjjaoyama.net/"&gt;gym&lt;/a&gt; with a great group of dedicated guys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a citizen of Japan, home to numerous traditional martial arts, it is perhaps a bit ironic that I am blogging about a Brazilian system (although even BJJ has its roots in classical Japanese juu-jutsu).  Regardless, I thought that other BJJ students around the world would enjoy reading about what training is like in central Tokyo.  I will try to keep things interesting!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Matt Helmer</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2013 08:37:14 +0900</pubDate><guid>tag:metahikari.github.com,2013-01-13:about-metahikari.html</guid></item></channel></rss>